Guide to the Anderson family Papers, 1848-1963
Department of Special Collections
- E, Total E 76
  - Ellsworth, A.A. 1885colleague. Braintree, Mass., 10
  - Everts, Katherine Javell
  - Everett, Laura
  - Ewing, T.D. 1888Parsons College, Iowa.
    The Evening Post letter regarding Professor Ross by M.B.A.
- F, Total 128
  - Failing, Henry 1887family friends of Edward
  - Failing, James 1890Coffin Anderson..father of M.B.A.
  - Failing, Edward 1890also business relationship.
  - Fairman, Emma 1895re: Balfour-sympathy.
  - Ferreri, G. 1900Italian friend.
  - Field, Charles 1905Stanford's "bard". Student of M.B.A., 2
  - Finch, Mrs. E. O. 1895re: Balfour's death. from San Jose.
  - Finley, John 1898-1933Knox College. later literary editor New York Times., 6
  - Flint, T.B. 1899, 5
  - Forbush, Rev. T.B. 1890American Unitarian Asso., 3
  - Franklin, Effie Scott 1914wife of Dr. Franklin..Chemistry Dept. Stanford., 3
  - French, Alice 1889, 5
  - French, Sizanne Students of M.B.A., 1
  - French, P. Students of M.B.A.
  - Funk and Wagnalls Co Publishers.
  - Furness, Howard, 2
  - Fukukita, Y. 1905Student. M.B.A., 2; F. Total 40
    Special Folder
  - Flugel, Ewald, 68
  - French Wounded Emergency Fund 1917, 20
    1 letter from Lou Henry Hoover, undated
- G, Total G 142
  - Gelvin, Rebe Robins
  - Gemboni, Ada
  - Garrison, W.H.
  - Gatee, Merrill
  - Gayley, Charles Mills English Dept. Univ. of Calif.
  - Ghimento
  - Gibson, Cora
  - Gilbert, Charles Stanford Old Guard Faculty from Cornell.
  - Gilder, B.W.
  - Gilfillan, Dore
  - Ginn, Heath and Co.
  - Goddard, Jessie
  - Gordon, Elinor
  - Gould, Mary
  - Goss, William F.M.
  - Grandgent, C.H.
  - Grentham, Muriel
  - Greer, Cornelia and Medorem, 5
  - Griggs, Edward Howard Colleague., 46
  - Grim, Herman, 3
  - Grinell, J., G...... 92
  - Greydon, Ellen, Katharine, Mary, Julis, 50
- H, Total H 158
  - Haddock. W.
  - Hadley, Earl
  - Hale, William Bayard
  - Hall, Howard English Department..Stanford. Colleague, friend, 21
  - Hammatt, Edward, 2
  - Hammond, W.W., 2
  - Hardy, Irene Stanford.. poetess and family friend., 28
  - Harrington, Margaret
  - Harris Blanche, Mattie, Rosalie
  - Hart, J.M. 1884Colleague. Univ. of Cincinatti, 20
  - Hartung, W.
  - Haven, Martha
  - Harvey, L,M.
  - Hays, Alice Stanford.
  - Heagle, D
  - Heath, Harold (re: Malcolm)
  - D C Heath Publishers, 5
  - Hempel, Hans 1892Univ. of Michigan,..re: offer of post.
  - Hempl, George. Stanford
  - Henshaw, A.N. 1893re: position
  - Henry, Bassie Stanford student
  - Herrick, Lester Certified pub. acct for Mutual Building Loan ASSO.. San Jose... and College Park/This do.played important part in family finances.
  - Heywood, Florence. Student and friend. Stanford and Paris., 5
  - Hills, S.R.
  - Hinchley, Katherine
  - Hodell, Charles re: position on Stanford Faculty
  - Hodson, Caspar World Book Co. Publishers of Dante of M.B.A. One of nine publishers. Nine editions., 4
  - Holbrook, Agnes Ide 1889.Iowa, 8
  - Hollenbeck, C.E. 1877Butler University re: Masters Degree
  - Holman, Fleta
  - Holman, Fred Stanford Student
  - Holmes, Clars Stanford student.
  - Holt, Grace Stanford student.
  - Holt, Henry Publishers.
  - Hooper, Kate Stanford student.
  - Hoover, Lou Henry wife of Herbert Hoover., 4
  - Howard, John 1874Interesting gift to M.B.A., 5
  - Hope, Hazel.. Stanford student., 3
  - Houghton, Osgood and Co. Publishers, 4
  - Hudson, A.L. 1890re: course of lectures given by M.B.A.
  - Hudson, W.H. 1892Cornell University, 5
  - Huebsch, B.W. Publisher 1911 The Happy Teacher confirmation, 6
  - Huliney, Edward
  - Hulme, Edward M. 1921Univ. of Idaho. former student of MBA, 16
  - Humlin, Sarah
  - Hussey, Ethel Fountain (Mra. William) Lick Observatory 1901and 1916Detroit Observatory.
  - Hutchins, Joseph 1896Attorney-at-law
  - Huxley, John Brooks Sr. 1921London re: Translation..Divine Commedie Dante.
    Huxley St. John Brooks. Refiled under B
- I, Total I 2
  - Ingelow, Maude 1920Appreciation of poem by MBA
  - Ingersoll, R.G. 1899
- J
  - David Starr Jordan, Special Manuscript Box
  - Jordan, Susan 1st wife of David Sfarr Jordan July 8, 1878, 1
    On a Portrait of David Starr Jordan at the age of 21.
    Random reminiscences of our early acquaintance by Melville Best Anderson
    - 1880-1889, 53 letters
      from Indians State University to M.B.A. at
      Irvington Indians
      Galesburg, Illinois..Knox College.
      1886 Purdue University
    - 1890-1899, 13 letters
      from Indians University to M.B.A. at
      1) University of Iowa, Iowa City from Stanford University to M.B.A.
      Appointment of M.B.A. to Stanford University.
      Chair of English.
    - 1900-1910, 23 letters
      Nov 19, 1909 Letter from Carnegie Foundation concerning annual retiring allowance for M.B.A.
      Starting August 1, 1910 $ 2,200.00
    - 1911-1920, 47 letters
    - 1921-1927, 4 letters
  - Jack, O. W.
    Omitted from original summary
  - Jagemann, Hans C. G. von, 12 letters
  - James, Alice
  - James, E. O., 22 letters
  - James, Rosetta E.
  - Jappe, Thomas H.
  - Jenkins, Mr. and Mrs. Oliver P.
  - Jenks, J. W.
  - Jenness, Mr.
  - Jenness, James F.
  - Johnson, Charles L.
  - Johnson, D. Powell
  - Johnson, Jennet
  - Johnson, Josephine
  - Johnson, Oliver and Florence
  - Johnson, W. Carey
  - Johns, C. R.
  - Jones & Co. (builders)
  - Jones, Dorothy
  - Jones, G. I. & Co. Publishers
  - Jones, Mrs. William McKinley
  - Jordan, Mary A. Cousin of David Starr Jordan
  - Judy, Arthur M, 28 letters
  - Jury, Mrs. John G.
- K
  - Kankakee Line
  - Keeler, Charles, 8 letters
  - Kellogg, Mrs. Charlotte
  - Kellogg, N. J.
  - Kennedy, M. Lloyd
  - Kent, Charles W.
  - Kimball, Alice
  - Kimball, Ruth
  - King, Marguerite (Mrs. Prince)
  - Kipp, Kathryn R.
  - Kipp, May Louise
  - Kircher, T.
  - Kittridge, George Lyman
  - Knox College
  - Kummer, Blanche
- L, Total L 89
  - Lanefee, Mrs. William S
  - Lathrop, Alice student
  - Lathrop, H.B. Colleague. University of California, Stanford, University of Wisconsin., 11
  - Lawson, Catherina
  - Lay, Marietta, 1887student.. Knox College., 15
  - Lazarovich, Eleanor
  - Leavitt, Rowell student.. 1871..(fellow student)
  - Lockey, Mary 1905student..Stanford. Later principal of Castilleja School..Polo Alto.
  - Leddy, Mary 1902Student. Stanford.
  - Lees, Neville Dorothy Secretary of Gordon Craig..son of Ellen Terry. great English actress., 16
    also Gordon Craig letters in special folder
  - Lewis, A.P
  - Lewis, Elizabeth
  - Lewis, Mildred Chapman & Howard M.
  - L'Hote, Francina
  - Lindsley, Julia
  - Lindsley, A.A. 1875, 3
  - Little, Brown and Co. Publishers
  - Loofbourow, Leon L., 2
  - Long. Dr. M.D.
  - Lord, Augustus
  - Losse, Vivian
  - Lowrey, Dwight
  - Lummis, Charles Executive Director Archaeological Institute A.L. of America., 11
  - Luyster, A.L.
- M, Total M 235
  - Mac Aluter, James
  - Macbride, Harriet
  - Macbride, Thomas
  - Mac Coun, Townsend
  - Mac Ewan, E.J.
  - Mac Farland
    1 letter from M.B.A. also
  - Mac Nevin, Charles, 5
  - Mac Nevin, Cladys, 10
  - Magnusson, P.M., 2
  - Manton, Care, 6
  - Margerum, Winfield
  - Markam, Edwin, 3
    the poet & teacher
  - Martin, Percy Stanford. Prof. of History. Special friend., 2
  - Mason, Annie 1878.Friend, 22
  - Mason, Gertrude, 6
  - Mc Bride, J.H.
  - Mc Chesney, [1891?]
  - Mc Claire, Emlin, 1892-1895friend.. Iowa City.
  - Mc Clumphas
  - Mc Clurg, W. Lowrie 1889Pres. Delta Tau Delta Fraternity, Chicage, Illinois. to M.B.A. Iowa City. Asking what do to better standing of fraternity. M.B.A. asked to be member.declined., 3
  - Mc Cullock, Rev O. C. Letters from and regarding)
  - Mc Intyre, Miss
  - Mc Kay, T.A.
  - Mc Mahon, Anna B.
  - Merrill, E.W.
  - Merrill, Katherine
  - Merrill, Mina
  - Meyer, Alice
  - Meyer, Emma
  - Meyers, J.A. German correspondence, 5
  - Meyrick, Mary
  - Dorothy L'Hote Milles
  - Millimar, L.D.
  - Mirrielees, Edith-student- Prof. English.Stanford University
  - Mirrielees, Lucia-sister of Edith Mirrielees
  - Mivieri
  - Modern Language Association
  - Montgomery, Beatrice
  - Moore, E.
  - Moore, Marrietta L.
  - Moores, Charles
  - Moores, Janet, 5
  - Morris, Margaret
  - Morse, Robert C. 1889Friend, 17
  - Moses, Alice, Clara
  - Lemuel Moss, 5
  - Moulton, Josephine
  - Muir, John 1895-1909, 18
  - Mc Clure, S.S., 49
    Special Folder. Mc Clunes magazine 1893-1929
  - Mc Clure, Harriet. wife of S.S. Mc Clure, 2
- N, Total N 53.
  - Nadal, E.S.
  - Nash, John Henry Fine San Francisco printer..Dante M.B.A. terra-rima.. translation., 2; 200 copies of Divins Commedis.
  - Nation. The
  - Neidig, William, 3
  - Netherland American Steamship Co
  - New, Edmund H., 4
  - Newcomer, A.G. 1902Colleague..St nford English Dept. 1913Carric m., 18
  - Newcomer, Evangeline. wife of A.G. Newcomer., 2
  - Nicholson, Watson 1906Colleague.. Yale
  - Noble, Margarete 1892German connespondence.
  - Noble, Alvin 1889re: looking for post., 6
  - Nollen, J.S.
  - No. Name Club
  - Nonesuch Press
  - Noyes, George.. Colleague, at University of California., 1
- O, Total O 25
  - Oakford, Benjamin 1909Lawyer re: Arrowhead Hot Springs swindle.
  - O'Conner, Bizzemon 1879friend
  - Oregon-California R.R. Co re: Dante shipment.
  - Osborn, H.L. 1887friend, 4
  - Owen, Edward 1885-1886-1890university of Wisconsin - French Dept., 13
  - Oskison, John 1921..letter of appreciation
  - Outcalt, Irving 1914friend, 3
- P, Total P 95
  - Palmer, M.S. 1895Re: Balfour's death, friend., 2
  - Park, Florence
  - Parker, George 1905re: post, 13
  - Parker, Mary E. 1906from friend in Consulate Service-Russia
  - Passig, Viale
  - Patrick, G.T.W. Colleague, 6
  - Patterson (Miss)
  - Payns, Rosa
  - Peck, Anne, Marie, Mrs. T.W. 1890friends., 5
  - Peckham, Gertrude miss
  - Pearce, J.W., 5
  - Pease
  - Peery, Lessie
  - Perkins, Rufus Lord
  - Perkins, William
  - Perkins, W.R. 1888.Colleague..University of Iowa, 15
  - Petree, Nora
  - Phelan, A.E.
  - Phillips, John S. 1883-1920American Magazine -Publisher, 14
    one time associate, S.S. Mc Clure
  - Pierce, Miss
  - Pinchot, Gifford, 1
  - Pischl, Dr. Kaspar
  - Poo, Chew, 1903amusing letter from former servant.
  - Porter, Laura H
  - Potter, John E. and Co Publisher
  - Porter, Laura
  - Price, Thomas R. re; Post.. Columbia University 1900
  - Price, William W. Family friend, 3
  - Putman's G.P. and Sons Booksellers 1878-1887
- Q, Total Q 5
  - Quenzel, Paul 1892Eisleben, Germany, 4
  - Quackenbo, Nadal 1893re: post, 1
- R, Total R 82
  - Rae, Joan, William 1907friends, 6
  - Rawdon, Blanche
  - Red Star Line
  - Reid, Dr. W. T.
  - Reinhardt, Aurelia Henry. 1921Pres. Mills College, 3
  - Rendtorff, wife of colleague. German Dept. Stanford
  - Restano, Maria, Rosa, family of trusted Italian servant., 12
  - Revue, (Le Revue de Paris)
  - Rible, Blanche student, 6
  - Richardson, Archie
  - Ringstrom, Emma
  - Roberts, F. B. Colleague 1882..Indianapolis Seminary., 9
  - Robinson, Fred
  - Rogers, Mrs. Frederick
  - Rogers, C.B.
  - Rosenberry, Lois Kimball
  - Ross, Dr. J. F.
  - Roth, Dorothy
  - Rouix, Paul 1884-1905Paris. French., 12
  - Ross, E.A. colleague.. former Stanford Prof. expelled! 1901
    See Evening Post
  - Rudolph, A.J.
  - Rumbold, Dr. Thomas
  - Russell, Theresa
- S, Total S 147
  - Salisbury, Helen
  - Sampson, Martin 1889colleague, 7
  - Sargent, Denise
  - Schaffer, Charles A. colleague State Univ. of Iowa, 8
  - Schiemann, J.G. Schliemann
  - Schurman, J.G. 1892Cornell re: position
  - Schribner's, Charles and Sons
  - Siegle, Rose
  - Seelfe, L.C.
  - Beward, S.S. colleague Stanford. English Dept.
  - Sewell, May Wright Indianopolis Classical School..colleague 1887
  - Shambaugh, Berg C.
  - Sheldon, E.S.
  - May Louise Shipp
  - Shoemaker, Grace Gilman
  - Shurter, Edwin Colleague, 10
  - Simmons, Henry
  - Simonton, Dr. A.C.
  - Simpson, Mary
  - Sisson, Elinor W. friends
  - Sisson, L.E. friends
  - Skidmore, S.G. Co druggists
  - Slottenber
  - Smart, J.H.
  - Smart, Mary H.
  - Smith, Albert W. 1913Cornell colleague, 22
  - Smith, Brainard G. colleague
  - Smith, Charles Sprague
  - Smith, Edwin Burrett
  - Smith, Everett Colleague Stanford Journalism
  - Smith, Rosa
  - Smith, Stanley
  - Snow,, Mrs. S.S. 1879family friend, 1
  - Snow, Sydney B 1913family friend. Kings Chapel. Unitarian. Boston., 5
  - Societe Academique
  - Spencer, Hazel Hope student.friend, 6
  - Stallard, Dr. J.W.
  - Stasson, Edward J.
  - State Steamship Co
  - Steele, D.W. 1877
  - Steele, Minnie 1877, 9
  - Stempel, Guido 1888-1890, 20
  - Stephenson, Mathaniel 1872Univ. of Iowa Re: request for post.
  - Sterrett, Roger
  - Stiles, Henry
  - Stillman, J.M. Stanford.. colleague
  - Special folder; Stanford.
  - Stanford, Mrs. Leland 1897, 3
  - Stanford- assorted interests., 9
    These names were omitted from the original summary
  - Stoddard, F. H., 33
  - Stollenberg, C. S. (re: death of Malcolm)
  - Stone, Geo. W., 7
  - Stone, Gertrude
  - Strumberg, Chas. H.
  - Strunsky, Anna
  - Strunsky, Rose
  - Stua rt, Charles B.
  - Studtmuller, Miss
  - Super, Charles, W.
  - Shogren - Emma.
    The letters of Anna Strunsky and Rose Strunsky are filed under Walling.
- T, Total T 45.
  - Takoyams, K 1906amusing letter from ex. Japanese servant.
  - Tarbell, H.S.
  - Tate, C.M. (birthday poem)
  - Taylor, Edward
  - Tenny, Charles W. (Gooding College)
  - Thadbury, Robert
    refiled under Cadbury
  - Theobald, Harry C.
  - Theriot, George M.
  - Thoburn, Helen... student.. friend.
  - Thomas, Calvin
  - Thomas, Katherine Nash
  - Thompson, A.B.
  - Thompson, Ellen F.
  - Thompson, May Wright 1879, 7
  - Thrasher, W.M. 1883Butler University.
  - Tillinghast, B.F. 1880Publisher.
  - Todd, H.A.
  - Touring Club of Italy
  - Tpynbee, Paget Colleague....proof read much of translation of Divins Commedis, published by Oxford Press., 5
  - Traphagree, Miss
  - Trowbridge, Aline 1913Colleague French., 7
  - Trowbridge, V same family
  - Tyler, Moses Coit (Flugel appointment), 3
- U, Total U 6
  - Uniterian Church, 4
  - Unwin, T. Fisher London Publisher.. re: Dente, 2
- V, Total V 6
  - Van Meter American Anto Imperialist League, 2
  - Veblen, Andrew A. 1902Iows University, 2
  - Vernon, William Warren
  - Vivisni, Marchesa 1911Lease for Villa La Capponcina, Settignano, Florence
  - Vollmer, Henry, 2
- W, Total W 126
  - Wakefield, George W.
  - Wallace, W De Witt
  - Walling, Anna Strunsky Student.. friend part of 1905Socialist Party in U.S.A. Present in Russia at time of Revolution there. Married William English Walling, 15
    replaced in special folder
  - Walter, Herbert
  - Washburn, Jessica friend student, 18
  - Waxhard, Marjorie E.
  - Webster, Hazel Hope student, 3
  - Webb, Frances, Eva Lindsey, Winifred, 10
  - Westermann B and Co Publishers
  - White, H.S. Colleague Cornell University
  - William, J. Madison
  - Williams, Bertha (a friend from Iowa City)
  - Williams, D.W. Stanford
  - Williams, Ida M.
  - Williams, Lenore
  - Williams, M.B.
  - Williams, Tom and Dora. Stanford students and friends
  - Wilbur, Ray Lyman Stanford President., 6
  - Willard, E.W.
  - Willard, T. R. 1888Galesburg, Illinois, 10
  - Wilson, J.E.
  - Wilson, Kathryne
  - Wilson, Maude
  - Windsor, Mrs. James
  - Winter, A.
  - Wolfley, May
  - Wood, Charles Erskine Scott-Poet friend
  - Woodruff, E.H.
  - Woods Pansy M
  - World Book Co Publisher M.B.A. translation of Divina Commedia; Dante., 10
  - Wright, James O
  - Wyckoff, Charles 1883Colleague. Knox College, 4
  - Wylie, John
- X Y Z, Total XYZ 12
  - Yale 1891
  - Yocum, Eliza
  - Younkin, Lu
  - Young, J.B. 1891student
  - Zaber, Th. 1892German
  - Zahn, Gertrude, 1892German
  - Zacker, Emmabelle 1898German
ADDENDA TO LETTERS TO MELVILLE BEST ANDERSON
Accademia Dei Rossi in Siena; Alams, E. D.; Anderson, E. P.; Anderson, H. B.; Bailey, Walter B.; Baker, C. F.; Baker, Isadore; Bancroft, T. W.; Bank of Palo A lto; Barber, T. S.; Barnes, Erle; Bartlett, George, F.; Bement, Howard; Black, James, B.; Balckburn, F. A.; Blair, Vivian Losse; Bligen, John; Boisier; Braly, Miss; Brewer, Fisk P.; John C. Brinklee & Co.; Bundy, Sarah; Butler, Miss; Byrd, Jane; Butts, W. H.; Brooks, Huxley St. John; Belgian Relief Fund (K. R. Fairclough); Cody, B. C.; Caldwell, Ethel; Central Indiana Normal College; Chalmers, Patrick; Chandler, Mrs. A. E. (Maude Grover); Chislett, William; Christensen, F. W.; Cepulletti; Comstock, William W.; Comstock, C. E.; Coe, E. B.; Clute, O.; Closz, Jackb; Corbett, H. W.; Class List, July 1895. (First mention of Miss Agnes Smith); Corbaley, Kate; Corlou, Hiram; Cowdery; Cox, Charles, E.; Crandall, Miss; Cracroft, Alice; Crow, J. F.; Crowe, James; Culver, Miss; Connecticut Mutual Life Insurance Co.; Dickenson, M. C. (Museum of Nat. Hist, N. Y.); Donald, Eliz. C.; Cross Plains Dunne Co. William Hartung; Dunning, J. S.; E. Fan, (evidently a good friend); Edwards, E. J.; Eldred, May; Henrietta Failing,; Fisk Teachers Agency; Fletcher, Mrs.; Fletcher, B. B.; Flint, Maude; Flint, E. R.; Ford, Miss; Foster, E. K.; Foster, Nancy; Gauers, Alice H.; Gardner, Edith J.; Gilbert, Edward; Goddard, Charles; Gould, G. M.; Greer, George; Griffin, Mr. and Mrs. James; Hairs, R. B.; Hale, Edwin E.; Hammatt, Architect; Holbrook, Agnes; Holbrook, Ida Osmond; Holbrook, N. B.; Holman, John M.; Hoskins, L. M.; Howes, Abby C; Hare, R. B.; Hudson, Florence Amy; Hulsman, Evelyn; Lathrop, Miss; Lawrence University; Leonard, EllenG.; Lewens; Loundsbury, F. R.; Lum, J; Leuwgrafz, O. A.; Lyon, Milford; Maclihose, L. S.; MacRoberts, Mary Fraser; Mills, Dorothy Lhote; Miller, Ada J.; Milligan, Minnie; Milnes, Mrs. H. E.; MacBridge, Florence; Newcomer, Margaret; Newcomer, Evangeline; Parker, Helen McGilivray Parsons, Edith; Pack, D. F.; Peck, Mrs. W. F.; Rible, Lillie M.; Rice, Archie (envelope only); Richardson, Harriet F.; Rohr; Russell, William C.; Russell, William; Ryder, A. W.; Schliemann, J. L.; Schliemann, W. E.; Sewell, T. L.; Smith, Charles Foster; Smith, J. O.; Smith, J. P.; Snow, Dr. & Mrs. W. F.; Steele, Lotta M.; Tilton, J. D.; Todd, Gertrude; Tower, F. E.; Waterman, C. M.; Webster, R. M.; Werthman, Rosalie; Woodbury, G. E.; Yale, 1891; Yocum, Eliza; Younkin, Iu; Young, J. B.